Finding Aid for the Juan Aguilar Papers PASC-M.0107
UCLA Library Special Collections
Juan Aguilar papers
1907-1957
UCLA Library Special Collections
Aguilar, Juan
PASC-M.0107
4 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
The collection consists of music manuscripts, correspondence, scrapbooks, papers and photographs of Mexican-American composer, Dr. Juan A. Aguilar.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Acquisition Information
Beatrice Aguilar; gift; 1991
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942302993606533
Scope and Content
Collection consists of music manuscripts, correspondence, scrapbooks, papers and photographs of Mexican-American composer, Dr. Juan A. Aguilar.
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. Manuscripts
Series 2. Photographs
Series 3. Correspondence
Series 4. Programs
Series 5. Sound Recordings
Series 6. Miscellaneous
- Manuscripts, Series 1.
  - [untitled], 1984 July 10; piano (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adelita, 1927; piano (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Adelita, full score, parts, original manuscript (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Arcades de Roma, 1914 February 24; full score (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Arcades de Roma, 1914 February 24; parts (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Asturiana, orchestra (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Asturiana, piano, saxophone; piano score, piano and saxophone score (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Cantilena Imperial, parts (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Canzona All' Antico, parts (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Chiquillo del Alma Mia (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Concierto, 1911 November 10; piano, orchestra (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Concierto, 1911 November 10; instrumental parts (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Concierto para Piano y Orquesta, piano and orchestra reduction (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Consuelo: Concert Valse for Piano Solo, 1927; sheet music (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Contra la Corriente, parts (Box 4, Folder 23)
    General note
    Last two sections only.
  - Contra la Corriente, parts (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Contra la Corriente. Cantilena Nupcial, parts (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Contra la Corriente. Cocktail Party, parts (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Contra la Corriente. Sorpressa de Rosalia, parts (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Contra la Corriente. Tango, parts (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Contra la Corriente. Valse, full score (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Contra la Corriente. Vida de Rosalia, Luz de Lun, parts (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Coqueta (Polka)., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Scope and Contents note
    Parts.
  - Easter Mass, full score (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Ecos de Mexico, 1932 April 2; original parts (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - El Grano, parts (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - El Santo de Dona Luz (Contra la Corriente), parts (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Geisha Girl, 1933 March 20; parts (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Geisha Girl. Wisteria Vine, manuscript photocopy (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Ghosts of the Golden West, 05/26/1931 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Sketches.
  - Gran Coro a Cervantes., 07/12/1916. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Parts and piano-vocal score.
  - Granada., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Guajiras, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Full score.
  - Guajiras, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Guajiras (Moorish Suite, part 1)., 07/20/1934 (date performed at Hollywood Bowl).; 105 lvs. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    For orchestra.
  - Guajiras (Moorish Suite, part 1)., 07/20/1934 (date performed at Hollywood Bowl).; 59 pp. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Guajiras. Zapateo del Monte, piano (Box 8, Folder 7)
    2 copies.
  - Honeymoon - Valse (Contra la Corriente)., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Incidental Music to Pathe Freres Film d'Art "Faust", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Arranged by Charles P. Muller.
  - Japanese Suite, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - La Cuna Donde Naci (Box 5, Folder 13)
    Piano score.
  - La flor (Contra la Corriente)., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - La Folle Serenade., 04/29/1933 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Piano-vocal.
    By Louis Reix, with words by Maurice Dufresne.
  - La Jesusita, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Arranged by Juan Aguilar.
  - Las Tres Pelonas, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Londres Polka (Contra la Corriente). (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - March (Moorish Suite), 08/27/1931 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Marcha/Oficio de Defuntos/Salve Regina/Veni Creator Spiritus., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Mexican Rhapsodie, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Mexican Rhapsody, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Mexican Rhapsody #3, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Mexican Rhapsody #3, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Original manuscript and copies of parts.
  - Mexican Rhaspody #3, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Minuet (Contra la Corriente)., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Moorish Festival, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Full Score.
  - Moorish Festival., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Moorish Festival: March., 07/20/1934 (date performed at Hollywood Bowl). (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Moorish Suite (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Photocopy of typewritten sheet, 1 lv.
    Acknowledgements by the composer.
  - Moorish Suite. Asturiana, orchestra (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Moorish Suite. Asturiana, instrumental parts (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Morenita., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Rhumba by Juan Aguilar.
  - Music Box (Contra la Corriente)., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Nocturno., 1911 (Published by Friedrich Hofmeister, Leipzig). (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Opus 102, no. 1 for piano.
  - Novelette (Contra la Corriente)., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Obertura., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Pastoral., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    For orchestra, no. 16.
  - Primera Impression (Contra la Corriente)., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Princesita., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Orchestra parts.
    Includes typewritten biography sheet.
  - Rapsodia No. 2., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Reveile (from Moorish Suite)., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Instrumental parts.
  - Reveille, ozalid copy (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Inscribed by the composer to Sr. D. Victor Franco.
  - Reveille (Moorish Suite), manuscript (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Reverie, strings, winds and timpani (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reverie, full score and instrumental parts (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Rhapsodie Mexicana, 1914 July 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Russian Gypsy Serenade, 1921; piano vocal score (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - San Diego: La Perla del Oceano, 1990; full score (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Composed by Carmen Prietto Stoecklin (close friend of Aguilar family).
  - Septimo, orchestra (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Shrine of Jizo, manuscript photocopy (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Shrine of Jizo, full score (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Somos Las Floristas de Madrid, piano conductor score, full score (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - To a Viking's Daughter, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Vexilla Regis, full score (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Zortzico, piano, violin, voice (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Photographs, Series 2.
  - Charles Walker, Pryor Moore, [unidentified], Jesus Varquez. Standing: Lorn Steinberger, Charles White, Louis Vilelle, Juan Aguilar, [2 unidentified men] (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Father Basel Frison with Juan Aguilar, ca 1940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Ignacio de Castillo, Dr. Frank Nagel, Juan Aguilar and C.W. Cadman (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Unidentified location.
  - Juan Aguilar, 1907 June 22 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Inscription to "Chole".
  - Juan Aguilar, aged 14 years., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Juan Aguilar, Pryor Moore and Charles Stewart (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Juan Aguilar., ca. 1910. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Loren Powell, Osmar Dietz, Philip Kahgan, Juan Aguilar, Bela Adams and Philip Musgrave (recording session) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Misa de Resurrection (chorus and orchestra), 1935 April 21 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Premiere performance of the work.
  - Pryor Moore, Alice Brag McGinty and Juan Aguilar (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Pryor Moore's orchestra (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - St. Vibiana's Cathedral Choir, circa 1940 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    With Juan Aguilar at the organ.
  - Wedding of Juan Aguilar and Solidad Gomez, circa 1905-07 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, Series 3.
  - Easter Mass (assorted correspondence), 1926 April (Box 5, Folder 18)
    Typewritten copies of assorted correspondence regarding KMTR radio's broadcast of Juan Aguilar's "Easter Mass".
  - From: Florence M. Irish, 1934 July 18 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Regarding: Artist's and Conductor's Breakfast, held by the Symphony Society of the Hollywood Bowl on July 24, 1934.
  - From: Mrs. G.W. Ballard, 1937 February 12 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Regarding the arrangement of "Goddess of Liberty" for brass band.
  - Regarding "Russian Gypsy Serenade", 1941 March 17 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    To Mr. Roman Navarro from Martha Cumacho.
  - Regarding Aguilar Accomplishments and Compositions, 1933 April 5 - June 26 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Photocopies of thre letters from Elmer Clifton, Hugo Rosenfeld and Arthur Lange to Juan Aguilar, regarding compositions and other accomplishments of Juan Aguilar.
  - Regarding Juan Aguilar and the Musician's Protective Union (Assorted Correspondence), 1916-1917 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Programs, Series 4.
  - Everyman, 1936 September 10-17 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Performance took place at the Hollywood Bowl.
  - Holy Trinity Church (Los Angeles) Easter Sunday Performance, 1935 April 21 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Otto Ploetz Recital, 1928 October 21 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Otto Ploetz - recital with the Jonathan Club Orchestra.
  - Turn to the Right, 1920 May 16 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Program from a performance of "Turn to the RIght" by Winchell Smith and John E. Hazzard at the Majestic Theatre in Los Angeles.
- Sound Recordings, Series 5.
  - Cada Loco Con Su Tema, Mulata Soy Yo, 1 10" sound disc (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - California Christmas, Blue Again, 2 7" sound discs (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Cielo Andaluz, 1955 May 18; 1 10" sound disc (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Continuation of Mass in G, 1 10" sound disc (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - End of Mass in G, Organ Solo (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Juan Aguilar performing.
    10" disc
  - Giordano, 1 10" sound disc (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Mass in G, 1 10" sound disc (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Organ Solo, 1 10" sound disc (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Princessita, 1 10" sound disc (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Record Album, 6 10" sound discs (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Contains 6 untitled (possibly blank) 10" discs.
  - To a Viking's Daughter, Mohave Moods, 1 10" sound disc (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Vexilla Regis, 1 10" sound disc (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Vexilla Regis (part 2), Organ Solo, 1 10" sound disc (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Viking's Daughter, 1 10" sound disc (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Also performed by Carmen Prietto, soprano.
- Miscellaneous, Series 6.
  - Grove Dictionary of Musicians Article (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Photocopy of article in Grove Dictionary of Musicians by Joseph Vernon.
  - Juan Aguilar Obituary, 1953 October (Box 3, Folder 14)
    As printed in Overture magazine.
  - Los Angeles Herald and Express Article, 1936 October 10 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Regarding Juan Aguilar.
  - Los Angeles Times Article, 1936 September 16 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Regarding the music of Juan Aguilar.
  - Moorish Suite Program Notes (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Receipt, September 1936 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Manuscript receipt regarding Juan Aguilar and performance of "Everyman" - California Festival Association.
  - Scrapbook, 1913-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Contains programs, correspondence and newspaper clippings from English and Spanish language newspapers.